It's the 10th century. Sicily. The
island that is nowadays part of Italy is
under Islamic rule. The island of Sicily
has been the battlefield and prize of
empires for thousands of years. For many
centuries, it came under the sway of
Muslim rulers who brought their faith
with them and shifted the island's
religious landscape. However, this shift
didn't last and Christian rule would
return to the island shortly after. But
how? In this video, we'll see how Sicily
went from a Muslim stronghold back to a
Christian ruled island. The island of
Sicily has a long and storied history.
At various points, it was ruled by
Greeks, Carthaginians, Romans, Vandals,
and Byzantines, to name a few. Its
central position in the Mediterranean
made it an essential part of projecting
power for multiple empires that fought
countless wars to take control of it.
The island became Christian under the
Roman Empire and remained so under
centuries of Byzantine rule. In 827, the
Muslim aglabids of Tunisia, vassels of
the Abbised Caliphate, invaded the
island to topple the Byzantine
government. The resulting campaigns
stretched on for decades as the
Sicilians bitterly resisted Muslim
invasion. One by one though the cities
fell.
Polarmo was taken in 831.
Msina in 843 and Syracuse in 878.
By the end of the 9th century, Muslims
had effective control of almost the
entire island.
Muslim rule in Sicily brought many
changes. The conquest had been brutal
and caused significant depopulation in
some Christian communities. In their
place, Muslim colonists settled and
shifted the religious landscape of the
island towards Islam. However, most of
the island's population was Christian
for most of the Muslim period. They were
subject to the Jiza tax paid by all
non-Muslims in Muslim lands, but they
were generally left alone to practice
their faith. Churches were allowed to
keep operating and the Muslim rulers did
not make a serious effort to convert the
masses to Islam. Still, through a
combination of immigration and
conversion, around half of Sicilles
population became Muslim by the middle
of the 11th century.
Sicily developed a rich and prosperous
society under Muslim rule. The island
saw the introduction of new farming
techniques and new crops like dates and
sugarcane that were valuable trading
goods.
Thanks to its geographic position,
Muslim rulers, and Christian population,
Sicily was perfectly positioned to
become one of the biggest trading hubs
in the Mediterranean and enjoyed
commerce with every power in the sea.
This turned Sicily into one of the
wealthiest and most vibrant societies in
Europe. This prosperity was a
double-edged sword. The Byzantines never
stopped trying to reclaim the island,
and the Italian states grew increasingly
interested as well. The ruling Muslims
also developed a strong sense of
identity and independence that led them
away from the rest of the Muslim world.
It also encouraged infighting among the
island's wealthy and ambitious nobles,
resulting in the overthrow of the ruling
aglabids by the rival Fatimids. In 909,
the Fatimids would move their power base
to Egypt, leaving another dynasty, the
Calbids, to rule Sicily in their place.
But Fatimid power would not last. By the
11th century, Sicily was plagued by
constant outside threats, eager to seize
the island for themselves. The Cowbids
faced conspiracies or open conflict with
the Muslim Zerids of North Africa, the
Byzantines, the Holy Roman Empire, and
the Italian states. They also faced
serious divisions on the island. In
1035, a devastating civil war erupted
between the Kalbid brothers, Emir
Alakal, and Abu Hafs. Abu Hops called in
the support of the North African Zerids
while Alakal appealed to the Byzantines.
Both brothers promised their foreign
ally friendship and cooperation from
their portion of Sicily. Abuhafs and the
Zerids successfully defeated and killed
Alakal before the Amir's Byzantine
allies could arrive. But the civil war
left Sicily weak and vulnerable. The
Byzantines realized that now was the
chance to reclaim Sicily for
Christianity. But it would not go quite
as they planned. A Byzantine army set
out in 1038 to conquer the island. The
army under General George Maniaakis
stopped first in Italy to recruit
mercenary support for their conquest.
Among those mercenaries were the
Normans. The Normans were descendants of
the Vikings who had settled in northern
France. They'd already earned themselves
a reputation as incredible warriors and
were highly sought after as mercenaries
across Europe. 300 Normans joined the
Byzantine army that landed in Sicily in
the summer of 1038. The Byzantine army
swiftly captured Msina and enjoyed a
string of easy successes against the
disorganized Muslims over the following
two years, resulting in the capture of
Syracuse in 1040. One Norman family in
particular, the Hotvilles distinguished
themselves through the campaign. William
of Hotville personally killed the Emir
Syracuse in battle by riding him off of
his horse, earning him the nickname of
William the Iron Arm. The Byzantine
successes did not last. General Maniacis
was replaced by a unic named Basil after
Maniacis had a spectacular falling out
with the emperor's young brother-in-law,
who was also the admiral of Maniacs'
fleet. Without Maniac's leadership, the
Byzantine campaign collapsed and the
Muslims were able to halt their advance.
The Normans grew frustrated with the
Byzantines for not giving them a fair
share of the spoils for Norman
contributions to the campaign and
returned to Italy. The Muslims reclaimed
most of the island from the Byzantines
in the following years, but the Normans
back in Italy were making incredible
progress as well. Following a war with
the Pope where the Normans won and
secured their place in Italy, the Pope
recognized the Normans as the Dukes of
the southern Italian regions, Apulia and
Calabria, as well as of Sicily. The
papacy had never controlled Sicily, nor
had the Normans, but the intention was
clear. The Normans wanted it for
themselves, and the Pope was giving his
stamp of approval for them to take it.
In 1061, the Hotville brothers, Robert
and Roger, launched a campaign to
capture Sicily from the Muslims once and
for all. Messina fell within a day. The
rivalries that had consumed Muslim
Sicily were so intense that the Muslim
Amir of Syracuse welcomed the Normans
and allied with them against the other
Muslims on the island. In 1063, Robert
Roger and the Amir defeated their Muslim
opponents at the Battle of Chami,
securing Norman presence on Sicily, but
not delivering a decisive blow to claim
the island entirely. In fact, the Norman
conquest of Sicily would take another 30
years. Frequent issues back in mainland
Italy regularly drew Robert back there
which resulted in repeated pauses of the
Sicilian campaign. Progress was slow,
but the Normans steadily whittleled down
their enemy. In 1068, they defeated the
Zerids and Calbids at the Battle of
Misilmary, which caused the Zerids to
abandon their intervention in Sicily.
Then in 1072, the Normans captured
Polarmo, securing control of most of the
island. Robert died in 1085 without
seeing the entire island conquered.
Roger continued the campaigns with a
daring attack on Syracuse in 1086.
According to Norman historians, Roger
led the attack on Syracuse in person and
boarded the Emir ship in the middle of
the battle. The Emir was terrified and
tried to escape only to fall in the
water and drown under the weight of his
armor. The surviving defenders withdrew
behind the city walls and only
surrendered 5 months later. The Normans
spent the next few years mopping up the
remaining Muslim towns and fortresses
across the island. But by 1091, Sicily
was fully under Norman control.
Christian control had returned to
Sicily, but the Muslims weren't going
anywhere anytime soon.
The Normans would go on to develop a
reputation as fierce crusaders and
defenders of the Catholic faith. It is
surprising then that Norman treatment of
Muslims in Sicily was notably tolerant
for the period. Over half of Sicily's
population was Muslim in 1091, and the
Normans wisely chose not to antagonize
most of their new subjects. There was no
significant persecution of Muslims
during or after the conquest, and they
were instead embraced as equal subjects.
Mosques and other Islamic institutions
were allowed to continue uninterrupted,
and Muslims could be found in every
aspect of Norman Sicilian society.
Muslim soldiers served as Norman armies.
Muslim engineers built their siege
equipment. Muslim bureaucrats collected
their taxes. And Muslim poets composed
art that was enjoyed and patronized by
the Norman ruling class. Sicily was a
symbol of cultural diversity and
cooperation with a mix of Muslim,
Catholic, and Eastern Christian
influences that produced one of the most
stable, peaceful, and prosperous
societies of the medieval period.
Arabic remained one of the official
languages of the island, and several of
the Norman kings learned it.
The island was one of the centers of
Islamic and Christian scholarship with a
constant exchange of ideas like
philosophy, theology, geography, and
literature that showed remarkable
cooperation between the faiths at a time
when Christian Muslim relations
elsewhere were strained thanks to the
Crusades.
But while Muslims remained an important
part of Sicily, they were undeniably a
shrinking one. The fact was that the
Normans were still devout Christians and
active crusaders. The elite classes were
dominated by Christianity and Muslims
were encouraged to convert to achieve
social advancement.
Like the Muslims had done after their
conquest, the Normans had also began
importing Christian settlers to populate
the island, mostly Italian and French.
Over the 200 years of Norman rule, the
number of Muslims slowly declined both
proportionally and in raw numbers as new
Christian society took hold. A similar
decline befell the Orthodox Christians
of the island who found themselves
displaced by Catholics. It was not a
violent decline, but it was a steady
one. However, the Normans would not rule
Sicily forever, and the end of Norman
rule would signal the true end of Muslim
Sicily. In 1184, William II of Sicily
was still without any heirs when the
Holy Roman Emperor Frederick Barbarosa
approached him with a marriage proposal.
William's aunt, who was actually younger
than William, to marry Prince Henry, the
future Holy Roman Emperor. Even at the
time it was a risky move. If William
died without heirs, then Sicily would
rightfully pass to Prince Henry.
However, he was confident that he would
have plenty of time to secure an heir
and agreed to the marriage anyway. 5
years later, William died childless.
Desperate to avoid foreign rule,
William's illegitimate cousin, Tank
declared himself king of Sicily. The
timing was both excellent and terrible.
On the one hand, Barbarosa was occupied
with the third crusade during which he
unceremoniously drowned, meaning that
the Holy Roman Empire was in no position
to press their claim in Sicily. On the
other hand, under medieval law, his son
Henry was now the legal heir to Sicily.
It was only a matter of time before the
new emperor came for Sicily.
Fortunately, Tenred didn't have to worry
for long since he died suddenly in 1194,
leaving the throne wide open for Henry.
Henry's coronation as king of Sicily in
Polmo Cathedral on Christmas Day 1194
marked the end of Norman Sicily and the
beginning of the end for Muslim Sicily,
too. Henry was a dreadful ruler for the
island. He cared nothing for Sicily and
brutally extracted resources and wealth
from it to fuel his ambitions elsewhere.
His reign was so oppressive that much of
the island broke out in open rebellion.
Norman nobles, Greek Christian subjects,
and Muslim peasants alike, rejected
Henry's reign as tyranny. Henry
responded with immense brutality,
executing rebel leaders and massacring
hundreds of people. Sicilles Muslims
suffered heavily. Henry's sudden death
in 1197 didn't make things better. His
son Frederick was still an infant, and
Sicily would remain in chaos for the
next 20 years. A succession of German
barons ruled while Prince Frederick was
raised under papal protection, and they
were just as hated as Henry. Resistance
continued across the island,
particularly by Muslim groups in western
Sicily. It took until 1220 for Frederick
II to return to the island and restore
order. By now, pockets of western Sicily
were effectively in the hands of Muslim
rebels under their leader, Ibn Abad. In
1222,
Frederick's armies marched west and
crushed these rebels. Ibn Abad was
executed, but Frederick feared that
someone would soon rise and take his
place. He decided it was better to
address the recurring uprisings once and
for all. Between 1222 and 1226,
Frederick ordered the total expulsion of
most Muslims from the island. By now,
there were only between 15 and 20,000 of
them left. Frederick had them deported
to the Italian town of Luchera in Apulia
instead. Once at Luchera, the Muslims
were treated well and given freedom to
worship and live as they pleased. The
few remaining Muslims of Sicily had
joined them. By the 1240s, Muslims had
all but vanished from Sicily. Sicily's
Muslim age was over, but it left its
mark in Sicily's unique culture, which
still bears the hallmarks of its
complicated history to this day.
If you'd like to help us keep creating
and get early access to our videos,
behindthe-scenes content, and other
perks, consider becoming a member right
here on YouTube or joining us on
Patreon. Every bit of support helps, and
as always, thank you so much for
watching.